Dear viewers, feast your eyes upon this ultimate super-lightweight machine.
視聴者　諸君
この超軽量　究極のマシンを見よ
斜め風も　推進力に変えてしまうという
最高のエアロホイール
This state-of-the-art aerofoil able to convert even a crosswind to a forward thrust...
サドルは　合成革なし　成型カーボンの板
This saddle of pure molded carbon-fiber with no synthetic leather...
追求された機能美は　もはや　一つの芸術である
This pursuit of function and form that has merged into a single work of art.
It goes without saying that to obtain such a machine required much sacrifice.
もちろん　このマシンを手に入れるために
あらゆるものを　犠牲にしてきた
Ignoring my studies, laboring at part-time jobs,
学業を捨て
バイトに励み
sparing not a second for anything other than my time on the bike...
自転車に乗る時間さえ惜しんで
このマシンに　懸けてきたのだ
しかし　週末は　しまなみ杯
I risked it all to obtain this machine.
But this weekend is the Shimanami Cup.
こいつで勝利はもらったも同然だ
そして　ウイニングランの先には
My win there is almost guaranteed.
And at the end of my winning run I'll finally be greeted by that rose-colored campus life!
いよいよ　ばら色のキャンパスライフが
Sorry, can you bring it up? It's open...
すいません　持ってきて
開いてるから
I am prepared for any contingency.
わたしは　あらゆることに　全ての対策を取る男である
This lock is unbreakable, save for using a hydraulic cutter...
これなら　油圧カッターでもないかぎり　切られることはない
ああ！？　ま…　待て！！
W-Wait!
That's my bicycle!
わ…　わたしの自転車だ！
Don't steal away my two years!
わたしの２年間を　持ってくな！
ちょっと…　あーっ
Give it back!
返せー！　ああ…
And just like that, the crystallization of my past two years goes down the drain.
しかし　あっさりと　わたしの２年間の結晶は
水泡に帰してしまった
They are called the Cheery Cycle Cleanup Corps.
やつらは　「自転車にこやか整理軍」といい
A mysterious autonomous circle that regulates illegal bicycle parking.
違法駐輪自転車を取り締まる　謎の自治サークルだ
At first they were a group staffed by volunteers
そもそもは　キャンパス内の自転車をひたすら整理することに
奉仕する　ボランティア団体だったが
diligently giving their time to maintain the campus,
but in recent years they've taken on a strange look,
近年では　奇妙に姿を変え
and forcibly remove any bicycle just a tad outside the designated area...
ちょっとでも駐輪スペースを出た自転車を
強制的に撤去し　その自転車は　二度と返ってこない
And those bicycles are never to be seen again.
The rumors are that they end up at bicycle rental shops around Kyoto,
噂では京都市内の　レンタサイクルに流れるとも
日本海に運ばれ　北の国に　売られていくともいわれている
or are transported across the Sea of Japan and sold to that country in the north.
最近では　学内のみならず　京都全域にも勢力を伸ばし
Lately they've expanded their influence beyond the campus to the entire city of Kyoto,
so one cannot let down one's guard even when venturing off-campus.
大学を出ても　油断はできない
"Watch out for this guy!"
"Never forgive! Cycle Cleanup Corps"
そんな平和な生活を　脅かす彼らは
京都の学生たちの　にっくき敵である
They are the hated enemy of all Kyoto college students,
and a threat to our peaceful daily lives.
Why has such a thing happened to me?
何故　こんなことに　なってしまったのか
責任者に問いただす必要がある
It is necessary for me to question the one responsible.
責任者は　どこか？
Who is responsible for this?
hitobito wa atsui kumo ni kao wo kakushiteru
人々は厚い雲で顔を隠してる
Humans hide their faces in front of thick clouds
iki ba no nai omoi wo zutto motte toideiru
行き場のない想いをずっと持って研いでいる
Getting more and more consumed by the feeling of getting nowhere
nani mo nai machi ni umorete mo sore demo ima demo
何もない街に埋もれても それでも 今でも
Even now, they're still buried in the same empty town
tsuranaru uindou ni
連なるウィンドウに
A perfect dream of dolls lined up
narabitatsu ningyou no marui yume
並び立つ人形の悪い夢
on a stretched out window
sore to mo soko ni kakurete
それとも倉庫に隠れて
Then they hide themselves away
fusaidetatte
塞いでたって
so that they can be covered up
hokori dake kabutte mitsukaranai
埃だけ被って見つからない
Wearing only their pride, they still can't find anything
dare no te ni datte furerarenai
誰の手にだって触れられない
They still aren't touched, no matter whose hands they're in
boku tachi no genzai wo kurikaesu koto darake demo
僕たちの現在を繰り返すことだらけでも
If we repeat this moment of ours properly,
sou itsuka kimi to deaou
そういつか君と出会おう
I will meet you someday
sonna hi wo omotte hibi wo ikou
そんな日を思って 日々を行こう
Until that day is here, I will keep on going
ikou
行こう
Going
Then I was a brand-spanking new freshman university student
当時ぴかぴかの大学１回生だったわたしの目の前には
and before my eyes were innumerable open doors to that rose-colored campus life.
ばら色のキャンパスライフへの扉が無数に開かれていた
しかし　わたしは　合格発表のときから
However, ever since I learned I'd passed the entrance exam
my heart had already been set on the allure of a single circle.
誘いを受けていた　あるサークルに心を決めていた
And that circle's name is...
その名は…
"Cycling Club Soleil"
There lay my future of pure, sparking gold.
そこには光り輝く　純金製の未来があった
黒髪の乙女たちと　くんずほぐれつの恋の　ランデブー
Together with the raven-haired maidens in love rendezvous' fierce contest.
場合によっては　二人乗りも辞さない
If the situation called for it, I'd even be willing to let them ride sitting behind me!
...is what I, an idiot beyond all redemption, had thought.
そう考えていた　わたしは　手の施しようのない　アホだった
Icarus's wings were made of hardened wax melted after he single-mindedly flew straight toward the sun.
太陽　求めて　飛んだばっかりに
ろうで固めた羽が解け　墜落した　イカロス
And I in pursuit of that rose-colored campus life was indeed no different,
ばら色の　キャンパスライフを求めた
わたしは　まさしく　それであり
for the Cycling Club was a club in name only; it was more like a hard-core cycling team.
サイクリング同好会は　同好会とは名ばかりの
ガチンコ自転車サークルであった
I was cast quickly into despair,
そうして早くも絶望しかけた　わたしの足元に
and before my feet was a creature with a face like a fish-man just risen from the sea.
海から上がってきた半魚人の　ような顔をした男がいた
You fiend! Sink back into the ocean!
貴様
速やかに海へ帰れ！
You say some pretty mean things.
あなた　ひどいことを　おっしゃる
僕は　あなたの同士ですよ
I am your compatriot!
That was my first contact with Ozu, as well as worst contact.
これが　小津との　ファーストコンタクトであり
ワーストコンタクトでもあった
I wonder what they find fun about rotating their legs so fast they wear away the cartilage?
膝の軟骨　すり減らしてまで　足を速く回転させて
何が楽しいんでしょうかねえ
Let's do something more fun!
もっと　楽しくいきましょうや
Hey.
おい！　ラン行くぞ
Let's go on a run.
Right!
はい
Even if you resist it, there's no escaping your fate!
運命にあらがっても　仕方ないですのに
Training was as harsh as you could imagine.
トレーニングは　思うさま苦しかった
But it was with the belief that I could overcome the suffering
しかし　この苦しみを　乗り越えてこそ
ばら色の未来が待っていると信じてわたしは
and reach my rose-colored future that I turned the pedals.
ペダルをこいだ
In the world of "roadies," only the fast are recognized and praised.
ローディーの世界では　速い者のみが
認められ賞賛される
Speed is king! Speed is cool!
速さこそ　正義だ！　速さこそ　カッコ良さだ！
高校時代は　運動部に　所属していたわけでもなく
In high school I didn't belong to any sports clubs.
In fact, I did as few activities as possible
むしろ　できるだけ活動せずに　息を潜めて
and just stayed cooped up with a bunch of other layabout guys.
同じように非活動的な男たちと　くすぶっているばかりだった
So a full-blown athletic team was far too heavy a burden for me to bear.
そんな　わたしにとって
本格的な体育会など　はなから荷が重過ぎた
Even attempting to train,
体を鍛えようにも　虚弱体質なので
with my feeble constitution there was no certainty of improvement to begin with,
そもそも　トレーニングがおぼつかない
もちろん大会で　いい結果を残せるはずもなく
and of course there was no way I'd place well in any competition.
And so I shuffled along, wasting my freshman year.
わたしは　ずるずると　１回生を無駄にしていった
As usual all you're eating is chicken like a damn fool.
相変わらず　アホみたいに　鶏肉ばかり　食ってますね
Shut up, this is the best source of protein!
うるさい　これが一番のタンパク源なんだ
My, my... Must be a struggle for a poor fellow like you.
やれやれ　金もないくせに　ご苦労なこっです
鶏肉なんかより　ねぎ付きタン塩食わせてください
Instead of chicken, how about letting me eat some salted tongue with green onions?
How 'bout you eat some of this!
これでも食らえ！
Ozu never showed his face in the circle, but he'd frequently show up in my room.
小津は　サークルには　顔を出さなかったが
"Don't be such a picky eater!"
わたしの部屋には　頻繁に訪ねてきた
"Eat it!"
Why? Because someone called Ozu's "Master" lives on the second floor
何でも　この下宿の２階に
小津の師匠なる人物が住んでいて
of this boarding house, and it seems Ozu comes to visit him.
そこへ通う　ついでらしい
おおかた　わい談の師匠であろうと　わたしは　推察していた
I surmised he was probably a master at telling lewd jokes or something.
Your eyebrows are raised.
まゆ毛が　つり上がってますよ
そんなに気を張って　どうなるんですか
Why so tense?
うるさい！　お前のように　無意義に過ごすつもりはないんだ
Shut up! I have no interest in wasting my time like you!
How cruel. I put a lot of effort into enjoying wasting my college years.
ひどいなあ
わたしは　無意義な学生生活を
力いっぱい　エンジョイしているのです
And you have no right to criticize me on that front.
とやかく言われる筋合いは　ございません
Go home!
帰れ！　わたしの足を引っ張るな！
Don't hold me back!
God damn him...
くそっ　あいつめ
"Bicycle Club"
うん？　こんな物を…
What's this?
In there was a cornucopia of information about all possible kinds of aerodynamic bicycle parts.
そこには古今東西　ありとあらゆる自転車や
エアロパーツについての情報が　満載であった
I have no physical strength.
ああ！わたしには体力がない　ならば
Therefore, how about I do battle with the specs of my bicycle?
自転車のスペックで　勝負するのはどうか
Was it not a path of escape, even for a weak person such as myself?
貧弱な　わたしにも　活路が開けるのではないか
Having seen the light, in my second year I embarked on a complete change of course.
光明が見えた　わたしは　２回生になって方向転換した
Thinking back on it now, it was only the beginning of yet greater unhappiness.
今　思えば　これが　さらなる不幸の始まりであった
To get your hands on a good bicycle takes money.
良い自転車を手に入れるには　金が掛かる
わずか１ｇ　２ｇを　軽くするために
A reduction of a mere 1 or 2 grams requires an immense amount of funds.
大量の金が必要になる
ホイール　タイヤ　シューズの軽量化
ハンドル　ステム　コンパクトクランク
Replacing the wheels, tires, and shoes with lighter versions...
The handlebar, the stem, a compact crank...
For me to obtain a somewhat decent bicycle,
少しでも　いい自転車を　手に入れるべく
わたしは　勉学そっちのけで　ありとあらゆるバイトに打ち込み
I left my studies to the side and dove into every part-time job there was,
時には　違法なバイトにまで　手を染めた
even dabbling in some illegal work.
I became nothing more than a saving fiend.
わたしは　ただひたすら　貯蓄の鬼となり
And finally in the winter of my second year, taking loans from my friends and acquaintances,
ついに２回生の冬　友人知人から借金をして
考え得るフルスペックマシンを　手に入れた
I got my hands on the full-spec machine I had been dreaming of.
What lightness!
何という軽さ
This bike is, indeed, my wings!
これは　そう　わたしの翼だ
I felt that I could fly anywhere with her!
彼女となら　どこまでも　飛べる気がした
Of course I had already heard the rumors of the Cheerful Cleanup Corps,
もちろん　にこやか整理軍の噂はかねてより聞いていたので
so I took extreme caution.
わたしは　細心の注意を払った
I was so enamored with my new bicycle I'd take her out with me wherever I went.
とはいえ　新しい自転車は　いとおしく
どこへ行くにも　つい彼女を　連れ出してしまうのだった
Sorry about this, Manami.
すまんな　まなみ
I had only let my guard down for a second.
一瞬の気の緩みだった
I hadn't expected the Cleanup Corps to go to such lengths.
まさか　整理軍のやつらが　ここまで強引な　やり口だとは
I would never see my beloved wheels again.
わたしの愛車は　おそらく　もう二度と返ってこない
Is this who I am now?
これが　今の　わたしだというのか
In the two years I have left, will I stay such a weakling?
この２年間で残されたのは　この貧弱な体だけだというのか
その事実に　目をつぶってはならぬ
I could not shut my eyes from that reality.
But nor could I stand to look on it.
しかし　いささか見るに耐えない
Manami!
まなみ！
まなみー！
Have you gone nuts?
気でもふれたか？
No. On the contrary, I have seen the error of my ways.
いえ　今までが　どうかしてたんです
わたしは　大切なものを　見失っていた
I had lost sight of something important.
Bought two years ago at the university co-op,
入学時に　生協で買って２年
my Manami had been with me through all my joys and sorrows.
ずっと苦楽を共にしてきたのは　この　まなみ号である
I, once mad with visions of road bikes, would no longer be led astray.
１度は　ロードバイクに　心奪われた
わたしだったがもう迷わない
Manami is for me, my true life-partner!
まなみ号こそが　わたしにとっての　人生の伴侶である
But fate soon tore Manami and I apart.
"Shimanami Cup"
しかし　運命が早くも　わたしと　まなみを引き裂いた
Manami... Have you seen my Manami?
まなみ…　わたしの　まなみは？
知らないよ
Nope.
I didn't even consider it,
はあっ！　考えられぬことだが
but it seems Manami was not considered a participating bike
まなみ号は出場車両でないと　勘違いされ
ゴール地点まで　運ばれてしまったという
and was transported to the finish area by mistake.
By the time I figured that out, a great deal of time had passed,
そのことが分かるまでに　大幅に時間がかかり
わたしがスタートしたの
レース開始から４時間たった　昼下がりであった
so I started the race four hours late and it was already after lunch.
The Shimanami Cup goes from Onomichi to Shikoku, crossing the bridges from island to island.
しまなみ杯は　尾道から四国まで
島々に架けられた橋を渡って　横断していく
After crossing one bridge,
橋を１つ越えるごとに
島に降りて海岸線を走り　また橋を上るという
you run along the coastline of the island, then climb up onto another bridge.
In other words, it's a strenuous up-down course.
アップダウンの激しいコースだ
Manami, why must you be so heavy?
まなみ　お前は何て重いんだ！
I wonder where all the other racers are?
レースの参加者たちは　今　どこを走っているのか
Or wait, is the race even still going on?
いや　果たして　まだレースは　行われているのか
Excuse me!
すみません！
えっ　まだいたの？
What? There's still people out there?
にぎやかしは　いらないんだよね
We don't need any entertainment.
Even though my only goal now was to stay on the course,
それでも　なお　完走だけを　目標としたが
as night fell I began to lose sight of the course indicators.
夜になり　コースの表示も見えなくなった
For what reason was I racing?
わたしは　何のために走っているのか
For what reason did I even go to college?
そもそも　何のために大学に入ったのか
Manami? What the hell!
まなみ号って　何だ！？
It's just a cheap-ass basket-bike!
単なるママチャリではないか！
Continuing with the news.
Today in Hiroshima prefecture, the 10th annual Shimanami Cup was held in Onomichi city.
今日　広島県　尾道市で
第１０回　しまなみ杯が開かれました
The 240 participants put on a fierce race,
総勢　２４０人のレーサーによる
熱いレースが繰り広げられ
and the winner with a splendid victory was Kyoto's Higuchi-san.
レースの結果　見事に優勝したのは　京都府の樋口さん
That's the crystallization of my past two years!
あれは　わたしの２年間の結晶だ！
"I worked hard for this day.
It has to be!
間違いない
応援してくれた　弟子たちのためにも
結果が出せたことは…
I'm very happy I could be victorious for my disciple who always cheered me on," he said.
Enough, enough! I'm going home!
もういい！　もういい！　帰る！！
Where had all this energy I'd expended the whole time vanished to?
今まで　わたしが使ってきた　膨大なエネルギーは
どこへ消えてしまったか？
This violates the conservation of energy!
エネルギー保存則に反する！計算が合わない
Does not compute!
これは　近代物理学への　冒とくではないか！
Is this not a blasphemy of modern physics?
While I was thinking of such things, morning dawned, then night fell,
そんなことを　考えているうちに朝が来て夜になり
また朝が来て夜になり
then morning again, then night, and when I came to, I had reached Kyamachi.
気が付くと　木屋町へと　やって来ていた
Your face is a face of extreme impatience... You are unsatisfied.
今の　あなたの顔は　大変　もどかしいという顔
不満ですね
I can sense your fiercely earnest talent.
あなたは　大変まじめで　才能も　おありのようじゃし
Quickly I did tip my hat to the old woman's keen insight.
老婆の慧眼に　わたしは早くも脱帽した
Anyways, I sense there is an opportunity you can't let pass by.
とにかく　好機を逃さないことが　肝心じゃ
Opportunity?
好機？
This opportunity is always dangling in front of your eyes.
好機は　いつでも　あなたの目の前に
ぶら下がってございます
Please grab it.
それを　つかまえてごらんなさい
That'll be 3,000 yen.
はい　３，０００円
You raised the prices again? And damn that was quick!
また値上がり！　っていうか早っ！
It seemed that I had somehow fallen into the sea of worthlessness.
わたしは　どうやら不毛の海へと落ちてしまったらしい
Or perhaps I had never even taken off to begin with.
いや　最初から飛び立ってさえ　ないのかもしれぬ
In the end I was fated to waste away my college life just as Ozu had said.
結局　わたしは　小津の言うとおり
無意義な学生生活を送る　運命なのだ
I apologize for abducting you like this.
さらってしまって　すみません
I'm taking you to my circle's shack.
このまま　わたしの　サークルボックスまで行きます
先輩に折り入って　お願いがあるのです
We have a serious favor to ask you, Senpai.
Akashi-san?
あっ！？　明石さん
Akashi-san was a student in the engineering department one year below me.
明石さんは　わたしの１つ下の学年で
工学部に所属していた
The previous year she was the sole female member registered to Soleil,
昨年　ソレイユに　唯一の女子部員として　席を置き
and amazingly won the overall victory at a road race held in Keage.
蹴上で行なわれた　ロードレースでは
何と　総合優勝を果たしていた
What are you going to use the prize money for?
優勝賞金は　何に使うの？
お答えする必要ありません
There's no reason for me to answer that.
She had sturdy legs and an air that didn't let others get near her,
そんな健脚にして　他を寄せ付けぬ
雰囲気を持つ　彼女だが
but she had no real interest in races and quit Soleil.
レースそのものには　興味がなかったらしく
She invested all the prize money in her current circle, it seems.
今では　ソレイユを辞めて
優勝賞金を全て　今のサークルに　つぎ込んでいるらしい
Here.
こちらです
I apologize for the shady look of the place.
怪しげな所で　すみません
I've brought him.
いらっしゃいました
You? You're the dropout from Soleil?
君か！
ソレイユから　脱落した人っていうのは
R-Right...
This is our club president.
こちら　うちの部長です
I see, you really do have a feeble body.
なるほど　実に頼りない体をしている
You're exactly the kind of man perfect to become a bird.
そういう人こそ　鳥人間には　ふさわしい
鳥人間？
Become a bird?
ようこそ！　わが　バードマンチームへ！
Welcome to our Birdman Team!
Weight, 59 kilograms.
体重５９ｋｇ
胸囲８０ｃｍ
Chest, 80 centimeters.
Waist, 70 centimeters.
ウエスト７０ｃｍ
Indeed, you have the ideal body.
さすが　理想的なボディーです
What in the world is this?
いったい　これは　何なのですか？
Akashi-kun is our star engineer, see.
明石君は　うちの　優秀なエンジニアでね
And she seems to be interested in you.
どうやら　君に興味があるらしい
こうして　機体は　おおかた　できているものの
We have the airframe almost completed, as you can see.
うちのサークルには　今
あれに　ふさわしい　パイロットがいないんです
But no one in the team is suitable to pilot it.
You don't have to do anything in particular.
何もしなくても構いません
ただ　先輩のその体で
パイロットになってくださいませんか？
So will you pilot it, with that perfect body you have right now?
えっ？
You're going to get in that plane.
君が　あの飛行機に乗るんだ
But I'm a complete weakling. I even dropped out from Soleil...
いや　しかし　わたしは　体力もないし
ソレイユでも　おちこぼれで…
Exactly!
それだ！
We need our pilot to be as frail as possible!
できるだけ貧弱な体が　パイロットには　不可欠だ！
Well, that's not all, but you are definitely our ideal pilot.
もちろん　それだけでは　ありませんが
先輩は　理想的なパイロットなんです
特別な練習は　いりません
There is no special training you will need.
ただ　そのままの体で　大会に来てください
Simply come to the competition as you are now.
Just take care of your body so you don't get the flu, okay?
インフルエンザに　かからないよう
体にだけは　気を付けてくれよ
What a sudden development.
うん　急な展開だ
It did feel a bit like I was forced into it,
有無を言わせぬ雰囲気だったが
要するに　体のいい　ただの捨て石ではないか
and isn't this just a nice way of saying "you're a stone falling into a lake"?
The Birdman contest is a cruel game where you pedal and pedal
「バードマン　コンテスト」とは
こげども　こげども
最後は　必ず海に落ちるという　難儀な競技だ
until you inevitably drop into the sea.
In other words, it didn't have to be me; it could have been anyone.
つまり　わたしでなくとも　誰でもよいのだ
あの高さから　真っ逆さまに　海面に…
And isn't it really scary to head straight into the sea from such a height?
怖いじゃないか！
It's unbearable! I can't take losing anymore!
みっともないし　これ以上　負けを　こじらせたくない
It was spring of last year, during the road race on Keage.
それは　去年の春　蹴上のロードレースであった
I had taken off with a good speed at first,
最初　勢い良く飛び出したものの
but I immediately got winded, and was staring up at the canal incline.
早速息切れした　わたしは
疎水のインクラインを　ぼーっと見上げていた
The power plant over there is quite wonderful.
あっ？　あそこの発電所は　すてきです
It's full of dubious machines, and stirs up my heart.
怪しげな機械が入り組んでいて　心かき立てられます
And it's especially lovely during sakura season.
確かに　桜の季節など格別
Akashi-san, shouldn't you be in a hurry?
あっ　明石さん　急がなくては
Aren't you the favorite to win the women's race?
女子優勝候補ではないか
Yes, I am.
そうでした
Then, I'll be off.
では　わたしはこれで
The sakura are very nice.
桜　すてきですね
And so Akashi-san won not only the woman's race, but the overall victory.
そうして　明石さんは　女子優勝どころか
総合優勝まで果たした
Back then I saw dangling from Akashi-san, the Mochiguman.
そのとき　わたしが見たものは
明石さんが　ぶら下げていた　モチグマンである
They come in sets of five, so it seemed like she had lost one.
５匹で一揃いなのを　１匹なくしてしまったらしい
Afterwards I came across it, and had continuously forgotten to return it till today.
その後　たまたま見つけた　モチグマンを
彼女に渡すのを忘れたまま　今日まで　きてしまった
This opportunity is always dangling in front of your eyes.
好機は　いつでも　あなたの目の前に
ぶら下がってございます
This body has already crashed once.
どうせ　一度は墜落した身だ
落ち方なら　心得ている
Falling is something I have firsthand knowledge of.
All I need to do is grit my teeth and launch with a shout.
心を決めて　えいやっと　飛ぶだけでいい
And then Akashi-san will surely come to me after I've fallen, with a smile on her face.
墜落した　わたしを　明石さんは　笑顔で迎えてくれるだろう
Then afterwards, I'll sit behind Akashi-san as she rides up the sakura-lined incline!
そして　その後は　明石さんの後ろに乗って
インクラインの桜を…
Wait! Can I allow myself to be addled by such feelings?
…って待て！　そんな　ふやけた思いでいいのか？
お前の夢は　まずい　くず切りのように
ぺなぺなで　甘いものでなかったはずだ
Your dreams shouldn't be so flimsy, weak, and limp noodled!
Is it really okay to lower my future to such a shameless fate?
ここで　おめおめと　未来を下方修正して　いいのか？
太陽を目指すことなく　地上で
のうのうと暮らして　何が　イカロスか！
To no longer shoot for the sun, but to live lazily on the ground? How is that Icarus?
I'd just be some kid with ugly-ass wings!
それでは　ただの　羽が目障りな男ではないか
Wavering in the gap between reality and fantasy,
理想と現実のはざまで　揺れ動きながら
exhausted by the tumultuous developments of the past few days
わたしは　ここ数日の　怒涛のような展開と
四国から京都へ　不眠不休で　帰ってきたことの疲れで
and my no-rest, no-sleep return from Shikoku,
泥のような眠りについた
I fell to sleep like a sack of potatoes.
Can you keep up with me?
わたしに　ついてこれるかな？
This man is named Jougasaki, and is president of the Move Circle "Misogi".
その男は　映画サークル　「ＭＩＳＯＧＩ」を
主催する　城ヶ崎という男だった
女の乳と　トレーニングを　生きがいとする
この男に　わたしは　教えを請うた
He's a man that lives for working out and women's boobs.
And I asked him to teach me.
That's right, I'd made my decision!
そう　わたしは決めたのだ
誰よりも遠く　誰よりも高く　飛翔してみせる
I'd fly farther than anyone, higher than anyone!
そして　優勝した暁には
And on the dawn of my victory,
Akashi-san will be sitting on the back of Minami as we ride up the sakura-lined incline!
まなみ号の後ろに　明石さんを乗せて
インクラインの桜を見に行くのだ！
Listen up. Victory is everything.
いいか！
勝利こそが　全てだ
I will not allow you to run from a battle and live aloof like that Higuchi guy!
戦うことを逃れ　ひょうひょうと生きる
樋口のような男を　わたしは　許さない！
男なら　勝利をつかめ！
If you're a man, then grab victory!
勝利と女の乳を　つかめ！
Grab victory, and grab women's tits!
Jougasaki-senpai's teachings were actually pretty clear-cut,
城ヶ崎先輩の教えは　実に明快であり
and my motivation rose to higher and higher levels.
わたしのモチベーションは　どんどん上昇していった
The Birdman contest was even televised, and the place for the circle to shine.
「バードマン　コンテスト」は　テレビ中継もされる
サークル活動の花形である
そこで優勝すれば
If I won, then I would no doubt gain the attention
京都全域の黒髪の乙女に　注目されること間違いなしだ
of raven-haired maiden from all around Kyoto.
明石さんのみならず
I bet I'd need to broaden my field of vision to other women than just Akashi-san.
これからはあ　らゆる女性を
視野に入れる必要があるだろう
But that is a trial all winners must face!
しかし　これは　勝者には　避けて通れぬ試練なのだ
Being the hero sure is tough!
まったく　ヒーローはつらいですな！
What have you done?!
君　何てことしてくれたんだ！
I said you were fine the way you were!
そのままでいいと　言ってたのに！
But now you've got muscles!
筋肉がついてるじゃないか！
台無しだ…
Everything's ruined!
But...
しかし…
Akashi-kun's plane is designed with extremely sensitive aviation tolerances!
明石君の飛行機は　とても厳密かつ繊細な
航空力学に基づいて　設計されているのだよ
Even a 10-gram difference in the pilot would mean redoing the entire blueprint!
体重が１０ｇでも変わると　それに応じて
図面を　引き直さねばならんのに！
Ruined! It's all ruined!
ああ　台無しだ　台無しだ～！
Enough! Akashi-kun, you be the pilot after all!
もういい！　やはり　明石君がパイロットやれ！
You and your muscles can get out of here!
君は　もう　その筋肉と一緒に　帰ってもらって　結構だ！
それでなくても　整理軍　対策で　頭がいっぱいなのに～！
And I already had my hands full thinking up countermeasures to the Cleanup Corps!
早く帰ってくれ！
Get out of here, now!
Akashi-kun, you hurry back to work, too!
明石君　君も早く作業に戻れ！
I apologize for getting you involved in this weird stuff.
すみませんでした　変なことに巻き込んでしまって
I apologize too, for not living up to your expectations.
わたしこそ　すまなかったね
期待に応えられなくて
いいえ
No, actually the problem was that you far surpassed them.
むしろ　期待に　応えられ過ぎてしまいました
Birdman is, after all, an absurd goal that goes against the reason of man.
バードマンというのは
そもそも　人間のことわりに反した不条理な行為です
だからこそ
That's why I was thinking that the pilot should be a person
そのパイロットは　無為なことに　魂を燃やせる
不毛な情熱が　不可欠だと考えました
with a soul charred by idleness and wasted passion.
I heard that after you finished the Shimanami Cup on a basket-bike,
しまなみ杯を　ママチャリで完走した後
you came all the way back from Shikoku.
そのまま　四国から　帰ってこられたと聞きました
That's an incredible waste of energy!
素晴らしい　不毛なエネルギーです
いや　あれは　狙って　やったわけでなく…
Uh, that wasn't exactly my intention...
That's why I asked you,
先輩に　お願いしたのは　そういうわけだったのですが
but the idea that you'd go so far as to train didn't figure into my calculations.
まさか　トレーニングまで　してくださるとは
わたしの計算違いでした
わたしも　まだまだですね
I suppose I still have a long way to go.
I apologize, but I have to redo the design now.
申し訳ありません　わたしは　設計の手直しが　ありますので
See you later.
これで
Before I knew it I had come to the Keage Incline.
気が付くと　わたしは蹴上の　インクラインに来ていた
I had prayed to come here with Akashi-san,
願わくば　ここへ　明石さんと来たかったが
but now I felt like the rose-colored campus life was slipping yet even farther away,
ばら色のキャンパスライフが
二度と手の届かない所へ遠ざかっていくように思われ
わたしは　心の中で泣いた
and my heart wept within me.
Maybe I'd be better off flowing down and trying and make my name
いっそ　このまま　琵琶湖に流れて
湖にすむ　妖怪ナスカボチャとして名をはせようか
as an Egg-Pumpkin youkai that lives in lake Biwa...
整理軍！　コートの男！
The Cleanup Corps!
The man in the trench coat!
Hey, Ozu!
おい　小津！
What the hell are you doing!
何してやがる！
Oops, you caught me.
あらっ！　見つかっちゃった
It's you!
お前が…
Keep it a secret, 'kay?
内緒にしといてくださいよ
It's an important source of funds for the Secret Society.
秘密結社の　大切な資金源ですから
This is Akashi-san's...
ふんっ！これは　明石さんの！
We're in recession, so bicycles alone aren't cutting it.
今は不景気ですから
自転車だけじゃ　やっていけないのですわ
What the hell are you doing?!
お前　何てことを！
A certain person up north is looking for a plane much like this to play with.
さる北のお方が　こんな
お遊びの飛行機を　探しているのですわ
It was just going to crash into Lake Biwa anyway, so this is a far better use, right?
どっちみち　琵琶湖に落ちるもんだから
有効利用でしょ？
And what about my bike?!
それじゃあ　わたしの自転車を…
You're the one that stole it!
盗んだのも　お前の手引きか！
I don't really concern myself with each one individually.
一つ一つは関知してません
いいじゃありませんか
Why not, eh?
わたしなりの愛と　捉えてくださいよ
It's how I show my love, so grab it while you can.
After all, it doesn't matter which path you take,
あなたは　どうやったって
今みたいな　ありさまに　なっちまうんですから
you'll keep ending up right where you are now.
Maybe you're right...
そうかもしれない…
Would it be so bad to give yourself up and go with the flow?
ならば　このまま　流れに身を任せるのも　悪くないっと
われわれは　運命の黒い糸で　結ばれているというわけです
We're connected by the black thread of fate, after all.
Will you help me?
手伝いませんか？
You've got debts, right?
あなた　借金あるんでしょう
京都中の自転車　回収して回りましょうよ
Let's go around Kyoto collecting bicycles.
Only if I can aim mainly at couples riding two to a bike.
なるべく　二人乗りしてるカップルを　重点的に狙おう
Sure thing! You do that.
ようがす
そうこなくっちゃ！
What is it?
どうした！？
I guess the jig's up.
バレちゃったみたいです
Looks like Akashi-san is coming.
はっ！？　明石さんたち　来るみたいです
Don't tell anyone about the Cleanup Corps, okay?
整理軍のこと口外しないでね
Might be bad for your health....
命　危ないですから
Hey!
おいっ！
いったい　何なんだ！
What the hell?
自転車整理軍のコートの男！
It's the trench coat man from the Cycle Cleanup Corps!
N-No! That's not it! Akashi-san, this is a misunderstanding!
ち…　違うんだ！
明石さん　これは誤解だ！
I didn't do it, The Cheery Cycle Cleanup Corps are actually...
わたしが　やったのではない
あくまで　これは　自転車にこやか整理軍が…
どういうことなんですか！
What is the meaning of this?
Explain it to me now!
説明してください！
You've got it all wrong!
違うんだぁー！
Senpai!
先輩！
Senpai, where are the brakes?
先輩！　ブレーキは？
I don't know!
分からん！
Senpai...
先輩！　飛び降りてください！
Jump off!
At this rate I'll crash into the pond.
このままでは　池に突っ込む
I have no choice but to try pedaling and fly!
こうなったら　ペダルをこいで飛んでみせる
Now's the time for my training to pay off!
今こそ　特訓の成果が　ものをいうときだ！
It's flying!
飛んだ！
Where are the pedals?
ペダル…　ペダルは？
Akashi-san, where are the pedals?
明石さん！　ペダルは　どこだ？
There aren't any!
そんなもん　ないです！
We're in the free-flying category!
自由飛行部門ですから～！
It finally dawned on me
ようやく　気が付いた
that this was all a truly wasted effort.
それが　まさに　不毛な努力であったと
Perhaps this all started from the moment I considered the cycling club.
その失敗は　サイクリング部に
胴上げされた瞬間から　始まっていたのかもしれぬ
もし　ほかのサークルを　選んでいれば　わたしは
If I had joined some other circle, I would have surely spent quite a different two years.
まったく別の　２年間を送っていただろう
何より　小津と出会ってしまったのは　最大の敗因である
Meeting Ozu was clearly the greatest catastrophe.
Could Icarus have ridden the wind had he not tried to so hard to flap his wings?
イカロスは　むやみに羽ばたかなければ
風に乗っていただろうか
tengoku iku tame mainichi kosotto
天国　いくため　毎日こそっと
In order to go to heaven. Everyday, I quietly
naishou de ii koto shiteta kedo
内緒で　いいこと　してたけど
and privately do good deeds
namida hitohira
涙ひとひら
But a single teardrop
atama kurakura
あたまくらくら
Sends my head spinning
ano ko hasuppa koi dorobou
あの娘　はすっぱ　恋泥棒
That stupid girl, that love thief
watashi kenage ii hito
わたしけなげ　いいひと
I am a good and pure person
kanawanakatta koigokoro
叶わなかった恋心
My longing heart was not fulfilled
kamisama doushite
神様どうして
Why, god?
yurusanakucha koi dorobou
ゆるさなくっちゃ恋泥棒
I must forgive her. That love thief
ano ko tabun ii hito
あの娘たぶん　いいひと
Maybe she was actually a good person
wasurenakucha konna koto
忘れなくっちゃこんなこと
I have to forget all these things
watashi wa tengoku
わたしは天国
I'm in heaven
yurusanakucha
ゆるさなくっちゃ
I have to forgive her!